<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>lab notebook</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://joshmontague.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://joshmontague.com/</id><updated>2015-12-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Transitioning From Lab Science To Data Science</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2015/lab-science-to-data-science/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2015-12-30:posts/2015/lab-science-to-data-science/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, I turned in my Ph.D. dissertation and started working as a data scientist at a technology (SaaS) startup. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="6" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"&gt;&lt;div style="padding:8px;"&gt; &lt;div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"&gt; &lt;div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/YAr0lMrjaE/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank"&gt;Done.  #gradschool #happyfriday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"&gt;A photo posted by Josh (@jrmontag) on &lt;time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2013-04-12T16:03:24+00:00"&gt;Apr 12, 2013 at 9:03am PDT&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, somewhere around once per month I get an email from someone in graduate school or in a postdoctoral research position looking for advice and guidance in making a similar transition; these folks are generally looking to hop from their current career path in academia or lab-based research to one in "industry" (as the institution tends to call it). In my experience, "industry" just means anything but academia. This is also a popular conversation topic at local Meetups. In general, I really enjoy this conversation! &lt;a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=FYGM"&gt;FYGM&lt;/a&gt; is not my style. And since I was 100% clueless about the "how" when I began thinking about the same transition, I can sympathize with a desire for more explicit examples and a little advice, and I'm happy to share both of mine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even though I try to have these conversations with everyone who asks, I &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b2F-DItXtZs"&gt;do not scale very well&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, since my advice has largely remained the same for the last couple of years (it's a pretty slowly-evolving system), I figured it would be worthwhile to write it down and see if the SEO/Google Overlords can help spread the knowledge more efficiently than me having infinity coffee meetings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a general article about how to get a job as a &lt;del&gt;unicorn&lt;/del&gt; data scientist. That is a well-trod path, and if you spend some time &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=how%20to%20get%20a%20job%20as%20a%20data%20scientist"&gt;googling&lt;/a&gt;, you will find a never-ending list of suggestions. This article is about the ~5-step path that worked for me when moving from laboratory research science to the technology industry. It also includes some suggestions I'd probably make to an earlier version of me, given the chance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before getting started, I should be honest that this article is not representative of the nonlinear, indecisive, sometimes high-anxiety, and often back-tracking path that I actually took. And while it's valuable to acknowledge those processes (you may experience them too!), I don't think that story - which is really about the way my brain works - is the one that matters. Instead, these notes are the result of reflection and hindsight - a consolidation and compression of the things that seemed to work in my case. There's also a high probability of hindsight bias, so take it all with a grain of salt.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Foreword&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numbered sections below represent the portions of the journey that seem logically separated in my mind. But, importantly, they weren't completely serial. Real life is messy and these things were all quite mixed together for me. And while we're being honest, let's also acknowledge that it's possible none of this will work for you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, it's probably clear that I'm not a paid motivational spearker; if you're still interested, let's carry on. If not, thanks for stopping by. Go enjoy some &lt;a href="http://giphy.com/search/panda/2"&gt;panda gifs&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="research"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1: (Self) Research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Understand what you want, and what exists.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with some context. My transition began about two-thirds of the way through a physics Ph.D. program. I had chosen graduate school because I enjoyed the learning process, challenging myself, and - most significantly - I wasn't ready to be done learning about physics. I started with the assumption that I would end up like all of the professors around me, working on research and teaching. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I genuinely enjoyed the pursuit of making a dent in the barrier of human knowledge.&lt;sup id="fnref:might"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:might" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/phd-school-in-pictures/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Ph.D. boundary" src="http://joshmontague.com/images/PhDKnowledge.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as I was beginning to think about the next step in my life I had a growing sense that those same careers I observed around me were not the best fit for me. Furthermore, in what should have been the most important signal (but was not truly appreciated until much later), the actual odds of ending up in a tenured faculty position at some point are incredibly small.&lt;sup id="fnref:faculty"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:faculty" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; By this time, I had also come to understand (and entertain) the idea of pursuing research in a small, private lab setting. In the area around the University of Colorado, there are many private companies that have spun out of successful professors' research groups.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I worked my Google-fu looking for hints at precedent; what might the rest of the world think I'd be well-suited to doing next? I spent a lot of time doing this in the evenings and - if I'm being honest - when my lab experiments failed and I was frustrated. My browser history began filling with queries like "career options for a phd in physics," and "alternative careers physics phd." One HR rep at an engineering firm also suggested I learn how to downplay my impending PhD on my resume. I did not apply for a job there.&lt;sup id="fnref:fiske"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fiske" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a physicist is wont to do, I tended toward thought experiments: what kinds of things do I enjoy? What would it feel like to do X every day? I began to hone in on this loosely-defined role of "data scientist" in the software and technology space, because it sounded like a great combination of tackling poorly-defined technical problems and potentially bringing value to a lot of people.&lt;sup id="fnref:ads"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ads" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Even better, it involved doing so at a much faster pace than my lab research. Encouragingly, I was also finding a number of articles that described having a background in physics as being a reasonable match for this role. While I don't think that a physics degree is provides greater preparation than, say, sociology, or economics, it was an encouraging idea at the time.&lt;sup id="fnref:fields"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fields" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though not exhaustive, here are some things you might include in your thought experiment:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What kind of work do you enjoy most?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Writing software? Working out theoretical solutions to problems? Designing new models? Writing technical reports? Giving presentations?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What kind of work environment do you prefer?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A small team? A large one? Startup or corporate culture?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How important are the company's values to you? If "very," what type of values resonate with you?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Working on Wall Street comes with a different set of core values than working at a public health non-profit.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How important is location? Is there a particular place you must be?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is working remotely a preferable scenario?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identify the things that you'd like, dislike, and also those on which you're not willing to compromise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the answers to questions like these is a helpful way to start and also an easier way to start drawing lines around what you want or do not want for your future. You might come out of this thought exercise with a list of companies at which you'd like to work, or maybe a list of duties and responsibilities you'd like. Either one is a win. Don't be concerned if you don't know the answers to these (and more) questions. As &lt;a href="http://blog.sciencegeekgirl.com/2010/01/05/how-a-scientist-becomes-a-freelance-science-writer/"&gt;Stephanie Chasteen writes (beautifully, and incredibly geeky) in an article about her own career path into science writing&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm like bacteria... thermophilic bacteria do not "know" that the hot spot is "over there." They have no overall map of their surroundings to direct their movement in a straight line towards what they seek. What they sense instead is a &lt;em&gt;local gradient&lt;/em&gt; - a small change, right next to them. It's a little warmer &lt;em&gt;that way.&lt;/em&gt; They move slightly. They feel it out again. Move. Feel. Move. The resulting  path is a somewhat jagged, but non-random, path toward the thing that they love. And so is mine... something perked up inside me. &lt;em&gt;That way,&lt;/em&gt; it's a little warmer &lt;em&gt;that way.&lt;/em&gt; And I took a step. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Suggestions for past me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take these thought experiments as far as you can. Really stew on them. Try to understand what options are out there for your work environment: day-to-day responsibilities, compensation and benefits, growth and development opportunity. Consider the company's values, reputation, and trajectory. For a first job out of academia (which is likely to be a hard-turn career change), you may not be able to be picky about all of these. But thinking through how they align with your personal values is still worth it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="double"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2: Double Duty&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that you are currently employed in some way (maybe a research assistant or a postdoc), and assuming you are not planning to quit tomorrow, you're actually in a really great spot to start preparing for this transition. As you start to get a sense for the kind of organization or role that would work for you (&lt;a href="#research"&gt;see section 1&lt;/a&gt;), you will eventually want to start looking into the technical details. That is, identifying the skills, tools, and frameworks that are typically used. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this phase is that you may get to "kill two birds with one stone": help you keep doing work at your current role, and prepare you to be immediately useful in your next role. It might mean installing new software on your lab computers, or maybe bringing in a personal computer. "Tools", here, is loosely defined; it might mean learning more (or starting to learn!) Java, or Scala, or Python, or Excel, or the bash shell, or a different kind of math, ... who knows. Well, actually you should know, based on your results from these first two sections.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've been doing research for years, you're likely already capable of doing magical things with software. In my lab years, I used things like LabView, Mathematica, Matlab, SPSS, Igor, OriginPro, Excel, and probably others I've forgotten. Universities are known for these massive, site-licensed software setups. You may have also written some extensions or customized plug-ins for these software tools, but that's unlikely to help you when you leave your lab. Aside from maybe Excel, I've never heard of anyone using these tools in a business setting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this step meant doing some extra work on my personal computer. In the lab I was doing a lot of analysis and approaching the start of dissertation writing. However, my work (software) environment was pretty comically far from where I spend my time today. In my lab, I used Windows XP systems, controled equipment (and did some analysis) with LabView, and did the rest of my analysis (and plotting) in OriginPro. From my googling and reading, it seemed the practitioners of the type of work that seemed most interesting to me were largely using R, Python, and some flavor of Linux command line. So, I started learning how to use those tools better, creating dissertation figures in R, manipulating some data in Python, and so on.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to learn these news skills, the internet provides. Depending on what level you come in, consider &lt;a href="http://www.codecademy.com/"&gt;codecademy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=list+of+moocs"&gt;MOOCs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://ocw.mit.edu/index.htm"&gt;open courseware&lt;/a&gt;, or just keep googling. For example, when I began learning Python, I started with codecademy and then moved to &lt;a href="http://learnpythonthehardway.org/book/"&gt;Learn Python The Hard Way&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Suggestions for past me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're unlikely to ever be in a situation like graduate school again. Though you're not getting paid much, your schedule's flexibility is at an all-time high. Use this time to progress your learning as fast as possible. Once you start growing your new skills, put them to use outside of your regular work. Share the results. Use your newly-learned programming skills to write a tiny piece of software that's interesting to you and put it on &lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Then build something else and put that up there, too. Start writing about what you're doing, why, and how. Keep doing this until forever. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing your interests and projects in this way will both make you better, and likely help you get a job. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="networking"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Intermission: Networking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, you should be gradually building the skillset you need to be capable of doing something on the day you arrive (if not, &lt;a href="#double"&gt;return to section 2&lt;/a&gt;). And, you're also hopefully getting a better sense of what kind of work you want to be doing and where (if not, &lt;a href="#research"&gt;return to section 1&lt;/a&gt;). It's time for the infamous "networking" step. This term gets thrown around pretty cynically, so let's just call it what it is: "talking to other people." For me, this step had the steepest learning curve, but was (and continues to be) the most valuable one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I won't go so far as to say this is mandatory, I think you're leaving a lot of possibilities on the table if you don't get out and talk to real people. I started by visiting my university's career services office and signing up for a bunch of "networking workshops." These particular sessions generally had two focuses: practice interacting with other humans, and understanding what you want out of a career. I'm pretty comfortable with the first part, and I had already invested dozens of hours on what I wanted back in &lt;a href="#research"&gt;section 1&lt;/a&gt;! To be fair, while these workshops weren't helpful for me, they were always packed full of people, so they could be helpful for you. They were all free events, and sometimes there was &lt;del&gt;grad student bait&lt;/del&gt; free food, so it's not a bad place to start. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my university career services events didn't prove useful, the local community more than made up for it. One of my top priorities (cf. &lt;a href="#research"&gt;section 1&lt;/a&gt;) was staying in the same area - roughly, the Denver Metro area. So getting out and interacting with people who were already a part of the technology community was hugely valuable. While I initially didn't know where to start, I did some googling to find local gatherings that sounded interesting, and looked for groups on &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/"&gt;Meetup&lt;/a&gt;. I also reached out on Twitter to people for information about events. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jrmontag"&gt;@jrmontag&lt;/a&gt; You&amp;#39;d probably love it. Tech talk among Boulder geeks. Jokes, relaxed atmosphere. Every other Tues at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AtlasPurveyors"&gt;@AtlasPurveyors&lt;/a&gt; :-) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bocc?src=hash"&gt;#bocc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ef Rodriguez (@pug) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pug/status/28796728094"&gt;October 26, 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I just started going to events and talking to folks, asking them about what they did and where they worked! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, there's a crucial piece to this particular form of networking: not asking for a job. Maybe that's obvious to others, but I initially thought that was the main point of networking. It's true that the act of getting to know people in these contexts may actually lead to a discussion about jobs and open positions. But in my experience so far, the dividends are much higher when you just focus on getting to know who people are and what their interests are. This way, you're becoming part of a community, not just a local employee.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Suggestions for past me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk to as many people as you possibly can. Since you have introvert tendencies, this might be uncomfortable sometimes. Nevertheless, it will pay off in a relatively short amount of time (and hopefully continue to do so in the long run).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a few new friends; you're bound to meet someone with similar interests eventually. Learn who you &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; want to talk to anymore. Connect with people online; at the very least, find them on Twitter. I can't say I've gotten any professional value out of LinkedIn yet, but give that a shot, too (I'm obviously biased, but I think Twitter is a highly underated professional networking opportunity). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="escape"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4: Plan Your Escape Route&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You've scheduled "D-Day" ("Defense"). Or maybe you're working on scheduling, and you've got a dissertation committee that's agreed to participate. Either way, there is a faint light at the end of the tunnel! At this phase in the 5-step plan, the personal decisions are at an all-time high. You'll have to contemplate your own circumstances, needs, and desires to make the "right" choices here! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In year five of my program, I was forming a committee and focusing the topic of my dissertation. It's common for people in the program to stretch six years into six and a half, seven, or more. Sometimes this is because their committee requires more work of them, sometimes it's because "hey, at least I'm getting paid for this and I don't have any other ideas." I was not interested in staying longer than necessary (see all previous sections). Coincidentally, my primary advisor had been planning to go on sabatical the summer after my sixth year. I didn't want to deal with the added challenges and frictions of communication from half a world away, so I was highly motivated to wrap things up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of my efforts to meet people and understand local employment options (&lt;a href="#networking"&gt;see section 3&lt;/a&gt;), I had reached out to a local data scientist who's work I enjoyed reading. A little research showed that he had been in the same graduate program I was in; that seemed like enough shared experience to possibly start a conversation. I sent him a short message on Twitter mentioning that I was transitioning out of the graduate program, was interested in his field of work, and that I appreciated the work he was publishing online. The Twitter conversation evolved into a coffee meeting, then a couple more, and a couple months later we were discussing the possibility of an internship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the timing constraints I saw around me, I got to work designing my exit and getting my advisors to sign off on it.&lt;sup id="fnref:design"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:design" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I would crank my lab research to 11 for one more semester (Fall), and then hard stop on experiments at the end of the calendar year. In the Spring semester, I would only take a half-time research assistant appointment, and would spend that time working on my dissertation in preparation for an official Spring graduation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other "half" of my time would be spent in a three-month (approximately semester-long) internship working with that data scientist with whom I'd had the coffee meetings (our conversations had gone well, and we were both excited about the opportunity). Importantly, there were no guarantees about what would follow the internship, but that was fine; I was looking for experience more than anything else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Suggestions for past me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this phase, I think it's safe to say that I benefited from a lot of good fortune. First, I was lucky that the first opportunity I pursued with ambition turned out to be a great fit for me, personally. Second, it was lucky that the company was both in a position to hire an intern, and that that process coincided with my search. I think it would be wise to be pursue a couple of these opportunities in parallel. Putting all your eggs in one basket is never a good idea; having more options is a more resilient approach. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="cut"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;5: Cut The Cord&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time is just about up. You're approaching the transition period, and hopefully you've worked out all the details with everyone involved. If you're approaching graduation, you've triple checked that you've met all the requirements and filed the paperwork by the right deadlines. How you get from one role to the next is a matter of preference, but there are many options. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this step was fortunately pretty smooth. The internship had gone well: it was productive, I got along with everyone, and we did some fun work. As we approached the end of the agreed-upon three-month period, I was offered a a full-time position (contigent on defending my dissertation). I defended, turned in my work (photo at the top of the post), and signed the offer letter within a couple of days. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're moving into some position (contract, full-time, etc.) that you've already set up, consider taking a week or two to decompress. If the end of your research experience is anywhere near as overwhelming as mine, everyone around you will benefit from you taking a little time to unwind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't have a position set up (and no promising leads), but you're committed to being done with research, consider taking some time for self-study (MOOCs, textbooks, etc) or attending a "bootcamp". The market for these &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/#q=data%20science%20bootcamp"&gt;"data science bootcamps"&lt;/a&gt; has exploded in the last couple of years. Generally, you apply to participate and give an organization some number of thousands of dollars. In exchange, you get an intense 6-12 week classroom-instruction and project-based curriculum designed to introduce you to software engineering and common data science topics. At the end, most of these programs have guaranteed interviews with large tech companies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's probably too early to tell if these programs are "worth it" (by whatever metric is most appropriate). But it's clear that they have incredibly high placement rates upon completion, so the investment might be worth it to you if you can afford it. Generally, getting an interview at a major technology company is not trivial! In the interest of full disclosure, I applied to (and was rejected from) one of these bootcamps. But I have friends who were successfully hired after completing them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Suggestions for past me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I did this step pretty well; I don't have much additional advice for past me. Taking a lot of time to ensure that I had considered all the details was crucial for getting support from everyone involved. While your graduate school advisors are hopefully supportive of your decisions, it was important to acknowledge that they may not have much advice or assistance to offer once I decided I was heading outside their circle of experience and expertise - academia.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a lot of words.&lt;sup id="fnref:year"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:year" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If you read this far, great job - you deserve a cookie. Or an apple, if that's more your style. I hope some of these words are helpful to someone. At the very least, the next time someone googles "how does a physics graduate student become a data scientist", there will be at least one more bit of anecdata to provide some ideas and suggestions. If this was helpful to you in any way, &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/jrmontag"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;; I'd be happy to hear it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck with &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; transition!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:might"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://matt.might.net/"&gt;Matt Might&lt;/a&gt;, a professor in &lt;a href="http://www.cs.utah.edu/"&gt;Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href="http://www.utah.edu/"&gt;University of Utah&lt;/a&gt;, created &lt;a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/phd-school-in-pictures/"&gt;The Illustrated Guide to a Ph.D.&lt;/a&gt; to explain what a Ph.D. is to new and aspiring graduate students. Matt has licensed the guide for sharing with &lt;a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/phd-school-in-pictures/#license"&gt;special terms under the Creative Commons license&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:might" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:faculty"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the most recent data I could find on retirement rate is from 2008, but compare the two-year combined estimate of &lt;a href="https://www.aip.org/statistics/reports/faculty-job-market-physics-astronomy-departments"&gt;retirements from physics faculty positions (Table 1)&lt;/a&gt; (378), with the number of &lt;a href="https://www.aip.org/statistics/reports/trends-physics-phds"&gt;doctorates conferred from the same time period (Table 1)&lt;/a&gt; (2,959). That's almost a 1:8 ratio. Additionally, consider that the number of open positions is likely less than (at most, equal to) the number of retirements, and the excess of applicants held over from each previous year may also be applying for these same roles. Finally, consider that graduate enrollment in every field except education &lt;a href="http://cgsnet.org/graduate-enrollment-and-degrees"&gt;has increased since 2008 (Figure 6)&lt;/a&gt;. I've obviously neglected the effects of subfield specialties (ie high-energy positions versus condensed matter), and many other subtleties. All that said, I think the point is still valid.  &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:faculty" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fiske"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, working through this process coincided with attending an annual APS March Meeting where I attended a session by Peter Fiske. He led a session based on &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=Fiske+Put+Your+Science+to+Work"&gt;his book exploring non-academic careers in science&lt;/a&gt;. I spent some time talking with him about non-academic careers for scientists and this effectively cinched the deal for me. I subsequently read his book (recommended!), and I'm still grateful for that fortunate encounter. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fiske" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ads"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was before I heard the now-famous line from Hammerbacher about &lt;a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3008436/takeaway/why-data-god-jeffrey-hammerbacher-left-facebook-found-cloudera"&gt;all the smart people working to get more people to click more ads&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ads" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fields"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would not say that physics, specifically, is necessarily the best field of study to prepare for the type of work I do currently. However, I do feel quite strongly that there are a few characteristics in a field of study that significantly improve the odds of success: training that is based in the scientific method, that relies heavily on mathematics, and that requires a significant investment of attention and effort in a poorly (or loosely) defined space. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fields" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:design"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This design phase was not trivial. The details involved understanding and taking advantage of some odd corners in the graduate school rules. A big component of this process was convincing my advisors that my unusual plan was good for them, too. While the details were important for making it all happen, they're not that interesting, obviously specific to my program, and aren't necessary for the overall picture.  &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:design" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:year"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, the first draft of this post was dated 2015-01-23. My one-year retrospective was enhanced by an extra year's worth of experience. I've also found it harder to make time for extras like writing in the world of full-time employment. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:year" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="career"></category><category term="transition"></category><category term="grad school"></category><category term="post doc"></category><category term="academia"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="physics"></category><category term="data science"></category><category term="longread"></category></entry><entry><title>Relieving #SciPy2015 FOMO</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2015/scipy2015-fomo/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2015-07-11:posts/2015/scipy2015-fomo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learning new things is incredible. Especially when you get to the point of building on top of growing skills in a particular domain. Over the last couple of years, I've learned a lot about Python, in particular for use in data science and analysis. I also really enjoy socializing with peers from the field at conferences, and the one Python-specific conference I attended (PyCon 2014) was a blast. Super friendly attendees, and also getting the chance to meet - in person - with folks who only previously manifested on Twitter and websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I can't attend every interesting conference. So when I saw that &lt;a href="http://scipy2015.scipy.org/"&gt;SciPy 2015&lt;/a&gt; just taking place in Austin, Texas this week, I felt a little bit of &lt;a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=fomo"&gt;FOMO&lt;/a&gt; for all the great stuff that was being presented. But, I was pleased to see a relatively consistent hashtag being used (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23scipy2015&amp;amp;src=tyah&amp;amp;vertical=default&amp;amp;f=tweets"&gt;#SciPy2015&lt;/a&gt;) to tie together content that was being shared on Twitter. One of the many reasons I love using Twitter for my professional development, is that so many people use it to share the new and interesting things they experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing that the next best thing to being there is to see the code, slide decks, and possibly video, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jrmontag/status/619184310663294977"&gt;I shared a Twitter search&lt;/a&gt; that I was using to occasionally check in on new content. That search was great while the conference was happening, but after the event is over the real-time search will be less helpful. So, today I saved &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search/?q=tutorial+OR+slides+OR+code+%23scipy2015+lang%3Aen+since%3A2015-07-06+until%3A2015-07-14+filter%3Alinks"&gt;a more specific version of the same search&lt;/a&gt; that includes a bit of the advanced search functionality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;requires #SciPy2015 hashtag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;requires one of: tutorial, code, slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;requires that the Tweet include a link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;requires that the Tweet is in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uses time windowing to focus on that one week (plus a couple of days)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way I can return to the results and consume them at whatever pace I need. There's an embedded version of this search below, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of note, Enthought also does a wonderful job of quickly getting the video recordings of the talks into &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLYx7XA2nY5Gcpabmu61kKcToLz0FapmHu"&gt;a super convenient playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="twitter-timeline" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=tutorial%20OR%20slides%20OR%20code%20%23scipy2015%20lang%3Aen%20since%3A2015-07-06%20until%3A2015-07-14%20filter%3Alinks" data-widget-id="619998240641912832"&gt;Tweets about tutorial OR slides OR code #scipy2015 lang:en since:2015-07-06 until:2015-07-14 filter:links&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script&gt;!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+"://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="data science"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="conference"></category><category term="twitter"></category></entry><entry><title>The Setup</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2014/the-setup/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2014-10-28:posts/2014/the-setup/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://usesthis.com/"&gt;The Setup&lt;/a&gt; has always been one of my favorite sites on the internet. I love seeing how other people - in vastly different careers - get their work done. Though I don't &lt;a href="http://warren.king.usesthis.com/"&gt;craft Chinese soliders out of cardboard&lt;/a&gt; or anything nearly that fascinating, I thought it would be a fun exercise to put together my own version. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who are you, and what do you do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jrmontag"&gt;Josh Montague&lt;/a&gt;, and I'm a data scientist at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jrmontag"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. As you might expect, there are many people at Twitter with that title and many do quite different work. My work is focused on helping customers of Twitter's &lt;a href="http://gnip.com/"&gt;data products&lt;/a&gt; knock their own products out of the park. In real-talk, that means I spend most of my time writing code and working closely with partners to conceptualize and prototype their products. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What hardware do you use?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use (and adore) my &lt;a href="http://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/B002TSIMW4/"&gt;Leuchterm notebook&lt;/a&gt; (8", with dots) for taking notes during phone calls, meetings, and any other times when typing on a laptop feels out of place or unnecessary. It's a fantastic thought-collector for all manner of doodles, brainstorms, projects, and data visualizations. In that notebook (and everywhere else, really), I'll write with whatever is around, but my preference is for ultra fine gel ballpoints. I always have to &lt;a href="http://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/B0058NN8NK"&gt;order them on Amazon&lt;/a&gt; because the fat-tipped, 0.7" version seems to have some kind of tyrannical reign over brick and mortar stores. Yes, I'm the guy who orders his pens on the internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our open office space, I use a pair of &lt;a href="http://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/B000065BPB"&gt;Sennheiser over-ear headphones&lt;/a&gt; when I need total focus; they have amazing passive noise cancellation (read: they're thick and insulated). While they are wonderful for listening to music, I can't concentrate on work tasks while listening to music, so I pretty much always have a &lt;a href="http://soundrown.com/"&gt;soundrown.com tab&lt;/a&gt; open and playing. My recommended recipe: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;coffee&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;shop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;waves&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rain&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;fire&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;white&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;noise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;coefficients&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;relative&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;maximum&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;setting&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;adjust&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;overall&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;volume&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;taste&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Senns are my first foray into &amp;gt;$20 headphones, and so far they've been great; if you need to quickly dispose of a bunch of money, my teammate has these insane &lt;a href="http://www.bose.com/controller?url=/shop_online/headphones/noise_cancelling_headphones/quietcomfort_20/index.jsp&amp;amp;Variant=qc20i"&gt;Bose in-ear things&lt;/a&gt; and I gasped outloud when I turned on the noise-cancellation. At least, I think I did. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I carry an iPhone 5 everywhere for all the uses in the world (+ multi-factor auth all the things). The battery is absolutely terrible, so I always keep &lt;a href="http://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/B00AANMVNQ"&gt;a portable battery&lt;/a&gt; in my bag. That might actually be one of the most worthwhile $25 I've ever spent.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work machine is an i7, 16-GB, 15" &lt;a href="http://store.apple.com/us/buy-mac/macbook-pro"&gt;MacBook Pro&lt;/a&gt;, which is usually connected to an external display of some sort (either an older Apple Cinema Display or a Dell). I tend to do my in-focus work on the biggest display available, and use the laptop display for other things that require less frequent attention (Twitter, taking notes, etc). At my seated desk, I bring the laptop display closer to eye-level with a &lt;a href="http://smile.amazon.com/Griffin-Technology-GC16034-Elevator-Laptop/dp/B0044RUSZM/"&gt;pretty simple stand&lt;/a&gt; that makes a big difference in the comfort of my neck. Whether seated or roaming around to the assorted standing desks in the office, I usually have a &lt;a href="http://store.apple.com/us/product/MB829LL/A/apple-magic-mouse"&gt;Magic Mouse&lt;/a&gt; and a plain old &lt;a href="http://store.apple.com/us/product/MB110LL/B/apple-keyboard-with-numeric-keypad-english-usa"&gt;USB keyboard&lt;/a&gt;. The MBP can be a little too heavy to lug around all the time (and a little too big for the bus commute, where I'm typically writing these posts) but the screen real estate and horsepower make it worth the effort. In my 8-year-old &lt;a href="http://www.timbuk2.com/customizer#/product/18-custom-classic-messenger-bag/size/4/customize"&gt;Timbuk2 messenger bag&lt;/a&gt;, the MBP lives in a &lt;a href="http://www.coteetciel.com/en-US/sleeves/filter/macbook_pro_15/"&gt;Côte&amp;amp;Ciel sleeve&lt;/a&gt; in an attempt to minimize bumps and spilled coffee. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And what software?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I spent most of my time. I try out lots of tools to make my work (and life) easier. For me, "easier" is always a balance between "more tools that each do one thing well" and "fewer tools that each do all sorts of things." It's a constant work in progress.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still using OS X 10.9 (Mavericks). When it comes to my work system, I'm rarely an early adopter because new OS updates always break environments. Always. I like to keep one project per "Desktop" in OSX, so I usually have seven or eight Desktops running at any one time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably spend 50% of my time in OS X's Terminal. Most of that time is spent in &lt;a href="http://www.vim.org/"&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt;. I write most things there: code (mostly Python and bash), documents (Markdown, text, and TeX), etc. The &lt;a href="http://ethanschoonover.com/solarized"&gt;solarized (dark)&lt;/a&gt; theme gives nice syntax highlighting contrast, and also keeps my eyes from getting tired (this will be a recurring theme). I keep meaning to try out &lt;a href="http://iterm2.com/features.html"&gt;iTerm&lt;/a&gt; but haven't gotten around to it. I spend a lot of time working on remote Linux servers, so I tend to keep it simple (and similar) on my own machine. When I'm feeling fancy, I'll fire up &lt;a href="https://code.google.com/p/macvim/"&gt;MacVim&lt;/a&gt; for some bonus mouse-clicking magic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd guess the next 45% of my time is spent in &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/chrome/?"&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;. Among all the articles I've opened to read (but will inevitably drop into the &lt;a href="http://getpocket.com/"&gt;Pocket&lt;/a&gt; black hole), you'll pretty much always find some combination of tabs open that include: &lt;a href="https://tweetdeck.twitter.com/"&gt;TweetDeck&lt;/a&gt;, all Google Apps (mail, cal, drive, and a handful of docs), &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/"&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/2/index.html"&gt;Python docs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, the HipChat &lt;a href="https://www.hipchat.com/emoticons"&gt;emoticon reference&lt;/a&gt; (chompy), &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira"&gt;JIRA&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://soundrown.com"&gt;soundrown&lt;/a&gt;, and often a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_distribution"&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; or two about whatever concept or techinique I'm trying to grok at the moment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also use a bunch of &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/category/extensions"&gt;Extensions&lt;/a&gt; because efficiency makes me incredibly happy: &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/blue-jeans/iedelpfmeejalepbpmmfbfnfoeojohpp"&gt;BlueJeans&lt;/a&gt; (video conferencing), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/pioclpoplcdbaefihamjohnefbikjilc"&gt;Evernote Web Clipper&lt;/a&gt; (quickly stash anything you come across online), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/hipbfijinpcgfogaopmgehiegacbhmob"&gt;feedly&lt;/a&gt; (rss), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/boadgeojelhgndaghljhdicfkmllpafd"&gt;Google Cast&lt;/a&gt; (for Chromecast), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/chklaanhfefbnpoihckbnefhakgolnmc"&gt;JSONView&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/gbammbheopgpmaagmckhpjbfgdfkpadb"&gt;XML Tree&lt;/a&gt; (prettify API responses), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/hdokiejnpimakedhajhdlcegeplioahd"&gt;LastPass&lt;/a&gt; (password manager), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/gpoigdifkoadgajcincpilkjmejcaanc"&gt;Markdown Reader&lt;/a&gt; (live rendering of local .md files - usually how I write and review these posts), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/laookkfknpbbblfpciffpaejjkokdgca"&gt;Momentum&lt;/a&gt; (eye candy), &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/niloccemoadcdkdjlinkgdfekeahmflj"&gt;Pocket&lt;/a&gt; (save-for-later), &lt;a href="http://www.smilealways.io/"&gt;Smile Always&lt;/a&gt; (get Amazon to donate to charity of your choice every time you buy things - thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hspter"&gt;@hspter&lt;/a&gt; for pointing this out!), and &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/ajjloplcjllkammemhenacfjcccockde"&gt;Tab-Snap&lt;/a&gt; (store giant tab list as restorable text file). The other Chrome "hack" that I use all the time is to use &lt;code&gt;Bookmarks | Bookmark All Tabs...&lt;/code&gt; to create a new bookmark folder with all the relevant pages for each project on which I'm working. This is especially helpful when there are (8 desktops) x (10 tabs) open and Chrome decides to crash.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last 5% of my time is spent switching between a host of other apps: &lt;a href="https://evernote.com/"&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt; (daily note-taking and long-term reference storage), &lt;a href="https://www.hipchat.com/"&gt;HipChat&lt;/a&gt; (team/org communication), &lt;a href="https://cyberduck.io/?l=en"&gt;Cyberduck&lt;/a&gt; (FTP/S3 browser), &lt;a href="http://www.gimp.org/"&gt;Gimp&lt;/a&gt; (for my amateur image creation needs), &lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/mac/keynote/"&gt;Keynote&lt;/a&gt; (for important presentations, GDocs for less important ones), &lt;a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/omnigraphsketcher/"&gt;OmniGraphSketcher/GraphSketcher&lt;/a&gt; (super handy for quick copypasta plotting of data from the command line), and &lt;a href="https://www.toggl.com/"&gt;Toggl&lt;/a&gt; (time tracking; incredibly enlightening if you've never tried it). Not too long ago, I would have also added &lt;a href="http://www.rstudio.com/"&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; (the amazing &lt;a href="http://www.r-project.org/"&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; IDE), but I've transitioned 99% of my R work into Python. I think this is mostly a function of how I learned to use R in the first place - a topic for another day.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a handful of other apps that are hugely valuable and always running in the background, too: &lt;a href="http://smilesoftware.com/TextExpander/index.html"&gt;TextExpander&lt;/a&gt; (saves time and typing all. over. the place.), &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/home"&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; (for both personal syncing - Camera Uploads! - and quick file sharing), &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/utc-bar/id525372278?mt=12"&gt;UTC Bar&lt;/a&gt; (our data at work lives in UTC and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jrmontag/status/524592677350694912"&gt;timezones are terrible&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href="https://justgetflux.com/"&gt;f.lux&lt;/a&gt; (adjusts your display's color temperature - helps reduce eye strain when working at night), &lt;a href="http://www.dejal.com/timeout/"&gt;Time Out&lt;/a&gt; (schedule periodic micro- and macro-breaks to reduce eye strain, and force walking breaks throughout the day; I use 30-second breaks every 20 minutes and 5-minute breaks every hour). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What would be your dream setup?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I'm pretty close to it, actually. Some small changes would include: a not-yet-possible 13" MacBook Air with the specs of the burly 15" Retina MBP, a pair of those magical &lt;a href="http://www.bose.com/controller?url=/shop_online/headphones/noise_cancelling_headphones/quietcomfort_20/index.jsp&amp;amp;Variant=qc20i"&gt;Bose headphones&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned earlier, a couple of &lt;a href="http://store.apple.com/us/product/MC914LL/B/apple-thunderbolt-display-27-inch?aid=www-k2-displays+-+index-n%40p&amp;amp;cp=k2-displays+-n%40p"&gt;27" displays&lt;/a&gt;, and a beautiful, automatic &lt;a href="http://www.nextdesks.com/terra"&gt;sit-to-stand desk&lt;/a&gt; would be a nice start. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I'll also note that at home I have an incredible 2007 MacBook (the white plastic one!) that's just barely hanging on. Don't tell Jony Ive or he'll probably come to my house and punch it. When it bites the dust, I hope to save for a &lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/macbook-air/"&gt;13" MacBook Air&lt;/a&gt; for personal projects. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="gear"></category><category term="hardware"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>Short: From plain text to JSON with jq</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2014/create-json-with-jq/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2014-09-28:posts/2014/create-json-with-jq/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most data in my work world is &lt;a href="http://www.json.org/"&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;, and so I use a lot of tools designed for that format. For example, we maintain (and use, all the time) &lt;a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/gnacs/"&gt;an activity parser&lt;/a&gt; that is designed for Gnip's &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Activity_Streams_(format)"&gt;Activity Stream&lt;/a&gt; data format from a half dozen different platforms. It handles all the assorted messages you might get from the API, and lets you pick and choose the output, among other things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A relatively new arrow in my quiver of tools at work is &lt;a href="http://stedolan.github.io/jq/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;jq&lt;/code&gt;, a fast and easy command-line JSON parser&lt;/a&gt;. This particular quote on the website is the best summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;jq&lt;/code&gt; is like &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; for JSON data – you can use it to slice and filter and map and transform structured data with the same ease that &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; and friends let you play with text.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently &lt;a href="http://support.gnip.com/articles/data-and-rule-management-with-jq.html"&gt;wrote on an article&lt;/a&gt; for our support site about using &lt;code&gt;jq&lt;/code&gt;; a kind of "tips and tricks with &lt;code&gt;jq&lt;/code&gt;". This gave me a great opportunity to experiment with something I'd been curious about: can &lt;code&gt;jq&lt;/code&gt; be used to &lt;em&gt;create&lt;/em&gt; JSON structures?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: the answer is yes! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="http://support.gnip.com/articles/data-and-rule-management-with-jq.html"&gt;click over there if you'd like to read the full article&lt;/a&gt;, but I'll add the punch line here. With a combination of &lt;code&gt;split&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;, the right command-line arguments, and an alias, I now use this regularly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;cat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;rules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.txt&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="err"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;tab-separated&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;dog&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;:en&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;tag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;:dogs:english&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;cat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;sample&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;:10&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="nt"&gt;tag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;:cats:0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;:gnip&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="nt"&gt;tag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;:user:gnip&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;jqrules&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;rules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.txt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;rules&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;dog lang:en&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;tag&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;tag:dogs:english&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;cat sample:10&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;tag&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;tag:cats:0.1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;from:gnip&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;tag&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;tag:user:gnip&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="cp"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you skim through &lt;a href="http://stedolan.github.io/jq/manual/"&gt;the documentation&lt;/a&gt;, it's clear that &lt;code&gt;jq&lt;/code&gt; can do a ton of awesome things; every time I learn a new one, it's a great boost in productivity. Happy JSON parsing (and, now, creating)!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="jq"></category><category term="command line"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>One Year In: Data Scientist</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2014/one-year-in-data-scientist/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2014-09-03:posts/2014/one-year-in-data-scientist/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Updated:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;after a particularly full week recently, another important topic came to mind that I felt would be valuable to include here: "keeping the wheels on the cart." You can find that section at the bottom.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer marked just over one year since I donned a goofy hat, shook my advisor's hand, promised my parents they'd never have to attend another graduation ceremony, and received the piece of paper that declared I was done with higher education.&lt;sup id="fnref:school"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:school" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; About the same time, I started working full-time as a data scientist at a small-ish software company. It seems like the one year mark is as good a time as any to pause and reflect, maybe for both my own sake and for that of anyone wondering, "Josh, what were the biggest changes you experienced in your first year that could be helpful for someone interested in making a similar transition?" Maybe no one is actually wondering that... but writing is healthy, so here you go anyway. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should start with some context; even though this kind of story will be different for everyone, I can at least give an idea about the "from" and "to". Before this transition, I spent six years in graduate school studying physics. As is common for these programs, there were two or three years of coursework followed by (and overlapping with) three or four years of research. When I left the lab, I started working full-time at a software (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_as_a_service"&gt;SaaS&lt;/a&gt;) company of about 50 people.&lt;sup id="fnref:path"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:path" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; My role (and that of my small team) was best described as "internal consultancy": doing research and providing answers to technical questions that came from sales, marketing, product, and engineering. This required varying levels of software development and analysis in a handful of languages and environments: predominantly a shell command line (bash), Python, and R. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, on to the more interesting stuff; what were the biggest changes in this transition? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first change I noticed was the perception and use of time. In graduate school, the relevant time scales were something along these lines: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;substantial research contribution&lt;/strong&gt; aka graduation: &lt;em&gt;five to six years&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;major result&lt;/strong&gt; journal article / funding proposal: &lt;em&gt;one year&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;minor result&lt;/strong&gt; conference paper / presentation: &lt;em&gt;three months&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fractional progress&lt;/strong&gt; incremental work toward minor results: &lt;em&gt;one week to one month&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly in my experimental research, "fractional progress" was simply the nitty gritty bit of getting actual work done: "successfully collecting dataset X," or "completing the analysis of dataset Y," or "finally building the op-amp with the proper gain and signal-to-noise ratio." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, I vividly recall the first urgent task I was assigned in my new role, which came with a followup of "we really need these answers soon - like tomorrow." Now, first and foremost: when made frequently, that kind of request can be a real red flag about the perceived value of your time. Thankfully, this was an exceptional case and most requests do not come with a priority-level-9 urgency. But that experience was an extreme example that frames the idea. Relevant time scales in the business world are shorter. I've found the scales to be more along these lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;major result&lt;/strong&gt; delivery of all projects for quarterly goals: &lt;em&gt;three months&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;minor result&lt;/strong&gt; success / progress on individual projects: &lt;em&gt;one month&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fractional progress&lt;/strong&gt; incremental work toward minor results: &lt;em&gt;one day to one week&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside: you may not have thought about time in units of "quarters" before, but in a business setting, you will. See also, the &lt;strong&gt;Business&lt;/strong&gt; section, below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, "fractional progress" / day-to-day work is pretty similar in scale, but covers many more potential areas: working through a particular data collection or analysis, bug fixes and new features in software and tools, customer conversations and support, putting together presentations for meetings or Meetups, and all manner of assorted other things. Any one of these may be a small (or large) part of a bigger project that provides business value.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Punchline: time is "shorter"; progress is measured more frequently.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Drivers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bigger change, still, was the shift in the motivation and drivers of the work. When I joined my research lab, there was already some research momentum from previous work. For my own research, I took a fork of that previous work and mostly tugged on the interesting threads to see where they led. Now, there were some implicit things at work there, too; for example, my advisor had enough experience to feel that my research was worthwhile and capable of being pitched to funding agencies. But, beyond that, the research directions were - as a favorite professor once described&lt;sup id="fnref:intuition"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:intuition" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - very much a "follow your nose" experience. Use your intuition and best judgement, but let the path be guided by the new and unexpected discoveries that occur along the way.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my new role, my team is guided by a similar sense of exploration within any particular project (undoubtedly related to fact that we're mostly former research scientists). But the selection of what projects we work on is driven much more by the business needs. Will this project help the industry move forward? Will it drive interest in our products or help us better understand the current use of our services? Does it directly benefit a customer? Does it ultimately lead to revenue for the company? Even though our team is not a software development team, most of our colleagues are; so we try to work using some of the same principles. This means "should we work on X?" is often decided by how close the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_story"&gt;user story&lt;/a&gt; gets to the actual business customer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Punchline: exploration and following intuition is required, but stay focused on things that will provide business value.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;s&gt;last&lt;/s&gt; penultimate idea I'll mention is around what it means to be a "business." I'll admit that I previously had approximately zero understanding of what came along with - and was considered part of - a business. At some level, it had to mean that there is a product or service (maybe more than one), and revenue came in from somewhere. For example, consumers could pay the business for the product. Or, consumers can use the product for free while being shown advertisements, and those advertisers would contribute revenue to the business for the opportunity to display ads. Or maybe all of the funding comes from an actual person or another business (angel or venture investments) in the hope that someday they'll create a successful product that ends up in one of the first two categories (and subsequently provide a return on investment for whomever provided the initial funds). Anyway, this is all perspective that I have &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, but I had no idea about this before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most overwhelming changes I experienced was the range of different people and teams involved; it turns out it takes a lot of cooperative, functional teams to make a successful business. Wrapping my head around the acronyms: BD, PMs, AMs, ... I struggled for quite a while trying to understand and internalize the roles that all of these people had. Oh, and those ones are: business development, product (or project) manager (or sometimes "product marketing", just to mess with you), and account managers. Finding out the roles that each of these groups of people (and all the rest!) have within the company is really helpful for understanding your own place and value. Don't be shy about asking folks what they do; it helps identify ways you can be assests for one another. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Punchlines: 1) funding has to come from somewhere; it's helpful to understand what - and to whom - your business owes its existence. 2) It takes a lot of different roles to really make a business rock.&lt;sup id="fnref:headcount"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:headcount" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It takes time to comprehend how everyone fills their niche, but learning the roles is crucial.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Keeping the wheels on the cart"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you're lucky (and good at what you do), there will always be more people requesting your time and effort than you have to give. Being in demand is typically a good thing. What this means, however, is that it's up to you to learn where to draw the lines around what you can successfully deliver. Additionally, even when you think you've drawn your lines reasonably and conservatively, unexpected things will arise. Curveballs are sneaky and inevitable. The server is down, the VPN isn't working, the file is 10x bigger than you thought it would be, there's some previously-unheard-of error for which the holy trinity (Google, StackOverflow, and IRC) are powerless. It happens; the key is not freaking out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the path gets rough and the produce (your projects) starts to fall out of the cart, the key is to focus on keeping the wheels on the cart. Keep your focus on preventing the wholesale collapse of the vehicle (and the subsequent disappointment of all involved stakeholders), and then sort out your issues. This may mean compromising on some of the results, so it's helpful to understand the minimum acceptable version. Ideally, your typical approach is to knock projects out of the park, so it's unlikely that anyone will notice the difference between that and these rare times when you've compromised. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transparency goes a long way, too. So, it may even be worth describing how your result differed from what you were hoping to achieve. Your mileage may vary.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Punchline: Learn your limits. Focus on keeping things moving when you approach those limits.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Now What?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what's the takeaway? Unfortunately, I can't help you figure out your new data-related role in a business outside of the research lab (but, hey, congrats on finding something!). But, I hope these thoughts shine a bit of light on some of the challenges I ran into related to the approach and awareness that I brought from my previous role in academic research. Everyone's circumstances are a little different, so you may not experience any of these; or maybe you have more. Either way, good luck in your new path!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:school"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barring, of course, any unexpected impulses to set off for an MBA or MD.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:school" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:path"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having writen this, it feels like there's also an opportunity for a companion article about the particular path that led me to now; I've added it to my list; stay tuned. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:path" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:intuition"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason this line was so memorable was that it came while our mid-career professor was trying to explain how we should use our intuition to solve path integrals in quantum mechanics.  &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:intuition" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:headcount"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is from the perspective of a company with ~50 people. At an earlier stage, there were five or six people, so everyone had to do their best to wear multiple hats.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:headcount" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="career"></category><category term="business"></category></entry><entry><title>Short: Create a Text File of U.S. State Names</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2014/state-names/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2014-06-09:posts/2014/state-names/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;While working on a project recently, I needed a simple list of US State names. My goal was to have a plain text file, one state per line, no funny business. The order of the states wasn't important. I always like a command-line challenge, so my first thought was "find the list online somewhere, &lt;code&gt;wget&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; as needed, slice up the html, and be done."&lt;sup id="fnref:woops"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:woops" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I went to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;the source of all information&lt;/a&gt;, and lo! there is a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_states_and_territories_of_the_United_States#States"&gt;table&lt;/a&gt; whose first column is all the US states. &lt;em&gt;#fistpump&lt;/em&gt; The only problem is I really wasn't planning to parse HTML for this little exercise; seems like a bit of overkill. But then I noted the &lt;code&gt;[edit]&lt;/code&gt; link next to the table name...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wikipedia table edit button" src="http://joshmontague.com/images/state-table.jpg" title="Yes, this will definitely work." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... and clicked through that to observe just the table source. Now this we can work with! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I simply copy/pasted this plain text into a file locally (say, &lt;code&gt;states-table.txt&lt;/code&gt;). Then, had a look:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;head -n30 states-table.txt 
&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;States&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;| &lt;span class="nv"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;wikitable sortable plainrowheaders&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;text-align: right;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
|+ States of the United States
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;12%|State
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1%|&lt;span class="o"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;List of U.S. state abbreviations|Abbr.&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;8%|&lt;span class="o"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;Capital city|Capital&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;12%|Largest city&lt;span class="o"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;#tag:ref|The largest city is the city in a state with the largest population in the [[city proper]]; [[metropolitan area]]s are not considered in this number.|group=upper-alpha|name=a}}&amp;lt;ref name=&amp;quot;State and Local Government Finances and Employment&amp;quot;&amp;gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/compendia/statab/2012/tables/12s0448.pdf|title=State and Local Government Finances and Employment|year=2012|publisher=[[United States Census Bureau]]|pages=284|type=pdf|accessdate=July 8, 2013}}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;11% data-sort-type&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;date&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;|Statehood
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;12%&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;|Population&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;2013 est&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;ref &lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;PopEstUS&amp;gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;cite web|url&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;http://www.census.gov/popest/data/state/totals/2013/tables/NST-EST2013-01.xls|title&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;Table 1. Annual Estimates of the Population &lt;span class="k"&gt;for &lt;/span&gt;the United States, Regions, States, and Puerto Rico: April 1, 2010 to July 1, 2013|format&lt;span class="o"&gt;=[[&lt;/span&gt;Microsoft Excel&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;|work&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;2013 Population Estimates|publisher&lt;span class="o"&gt;=[[&lt;/span&gt;United States Census Bureau&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;, Population Division|date&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;December 2013|accessdate&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;January 12, 2014&lt;span class="o"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;12%|Total area in mi&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;km&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;){{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;#tag:ref|Area figures are rounded to the nearest whole number.|group=upper-alpha|name=b}}&amp;lt;ref name=&amp;quot;2010 Census of Population and Housing&amp;quot;&amp;gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/prod/cen2010/cph-2-1.pdf|title=2010 Census of Population and Housing|date=September 2012|publisher=[[United States Census Bureau]]|pages=41|type=pdf|accessdate=July 8, 2013}}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;12%|Land area in mi&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;km&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;ref &lt;span class="nv"&gt;group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;upper-alpha &lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;b /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;ref &lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;2010 Census of Population and Housing&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; /&amp;gt;
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;12%|Water area in mi&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;km&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;ref &lt;span class="nv"&gt;group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;upper-alpha &lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;b /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;ref &lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;2010 Census of Population and Housing&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; /&amp;gt;
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1%|&lt;span class="o"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;List of United States congressional districts|House seat&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span class="o"&gt;)]]&lt;/span&gt;
|-
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;row&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;|&lt;span class="o"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;flag|Alabama&lt;span class="o"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;
|AL
|&lt;span class="o"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;Montgomery, Alabama|Montgomery&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;span class="o"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;Birmingham, Alabama|Birmingham&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
|December 14, 1819
|4,833,722
|&lt;span class="o"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;Convert|52420|mi2|km2|sigfig&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;6|abbr&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;values|sortable&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;on&lt;span class="o"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;span class="o"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;Convert|50645|mi2|km2|sigfig&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;6|abbr&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;values|sortable&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;on&lt;span class="o"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;span class="o"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;Convert|1775|mi2|km2|sigfig&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;4|abbr&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;values|sortable&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;on&lt;span class="o"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;
|7
|-
!scope&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;row&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;|&lt;span class="o"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;flag|Alaska&lt;span class="o"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;
|AK
|&lt;span class="o"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;Juneau, Alaska|Juneau&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;span class="o"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;Anchorage, Alaska|Anchorage&lt;span class="o"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
|January 3, 1959
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Clearly there's a lot of extra formatting for the other columns, but we can see a couple of the state names, so we can definitely observe some patterns. A simple &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; combination get us almost to the finish line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cat states-table.txt | grep &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;flag|&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; | sed &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;s/^.*flag|//;s/}}.*//&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
Alabama
Alaska
Arizona
Arkansas
California
Colorado
Connecticut
Delaware
Florida
Georgia &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;U.S. state&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;|name&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;Georgia
Hawaii
...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One extra bit of &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; formatting (strip anything that's not a letter)... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cat states-table.txt | grep &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;flag|&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; | sed &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;s/^.*flag|//;s/}}.*//;s/ [^a-Z].*$//&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
Alabama
Alaska
Arizona
Arkansas
California
Colorado
Connecticut
Delaware
Florida
Georgia
Hawaii
...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;... and we're good to go! (note: if you're doing this on OS X, you may have to swap that last &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; range for &lt;code&gt;[^a-zA-Z]&lt;/code&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's always nice to flex your command-line fu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:woops"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, I clearly could have spent an extra 30 seconds on google and just copypasta'd the results from a site like &lt;a href="http://liststates.com/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. But where's the fun in that?? &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:woops" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="short"></category><category term="bash"></category><category term="shell"></category><category term="munge"></category></entry><entry><title>Social Media Pulse Meetup Presentation</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2014/ab-pulse-talk/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2014-02-10:posts/2014/ab-pulse-talk/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of giving a short talk at one of my favorite local Meetups: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Analyze-Boulder/events/156806792/"&gt;AnalyzeBoulder&lt;/a&gt;. If you have the chance, this group of folks is a lot of fun to interact with. My talk was a short introduction to the space of social data, the importance of focusing on a single event in a "firehose" of realtime data, and a brief intro of the Social Media Pulse (SMP). The SMP is a model we have used to describe the data shared by e.g. Twitter users following an unprecedented and unexpected event like an earthquake. The slides are available online, &lt;a href="http://jrmontag.github.io/AnalyzeBoulder-SocialPulse/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jrmontag/AnalyzeBoulder-SocialPulse"&gt;&lt;img alt="Social Media Pulse" src="http://joshmontague.com/images/AB-pulse.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also used the presentation as an opportunity to learn how to create talks using the &lt;a href="http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/#/"&gt;reveal.js&lt;/a&gt; framework. I do love to Markdown all the things, so being able to write the talk almost entirely in Markdown (plus occasional javascript/html) was great. This proved to be a pretty fun platform for creating and delivering a talk - not needing to bring my computer to an event was nice. The presentation, all materials and data that went into it, and an IPython notebook for creating some of the figures are all contained in &lt;a href="https://github.com/jrmontag/AnalyzeBoulder-SocialPulse"&gt;the repo&lt;/a&gt;. There's also a template repo for creating your own reveal.js preso available &lt;a href="https://github.com/jrmontag/reveal-template"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="javascript"></category><category term="models"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Weekend Project: Build a Pelican-powered site on GitHub Pages</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2014/pelican-on-github/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2014-01-15:posts/2014/pelican-on-github/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: 
This post got pretty long, especially for the first real post on this site. But by boiling down my very non-linear experience and putting this in writing, I hope that you could read through this and make it all work in an hour or so. Let me know how close that is to reality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For quick, get-up-and-running web publishing, there is &lt;a href="http://tumblr.com"&gt;obviously&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://wordpress.com"&gt;no&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://blogger.com"&gt;shortage&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://medium.com"&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://ghost.org"&gt;platforms&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://subtle.com"&gt;out&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://typepad.com"&gt;there&lt;/a&gt; to use; most have a free, hosted version, too (I'm sure there are a million other options I've never heard of). I've certainly started and neglected my share of these platforms (or had them disappear ... RIP &lt;a href="http://posterous.com"&gt;posterous&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I've been super excited learning things my new career* and I was looking for an outlet for sharing (beyond the &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/jrmontag"&gt;140-character vignettes&lt;/a&gt;). I was looking for a combination of things: balance between "get your hands dirty" and "don't get hung up on too many details", balance between "keep it lightweight" and "give me some features", and balance between "let me learn something new" and "keep it relevant". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, my love for Python won out and I went for a static &lt;a href="https://pelican.readthedocs.org/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;-based solution hosted via &lt;a href="http://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. From this combination of things I get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python (the language with which I'm most familiar and love to use)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican (lightweight, fast, CLI tools for compiling and publishing, compose in Markdown) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;git / GitHub (sweet sweet version control, plus open-source-y website)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I'm still kicking the tires and figuring things out (I haven't even figured out how to change the theme yet), so far it's been fun to explore. There are some components that are still new to me, so I'm learning as I go. This edition of &lt;a href="http://joshmontague.com/tag/weekend.html"&gt;Weekend Project&lt;/a&gt; is just about getting the pieces up and running - better understanding will hopefully come down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Another good topic to write about in the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kicked this project off by reading two great posts by Martin Brochhaus (&lt;a href="http://martinbrochhaus.com/pelican2.html"&gt;newer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://martinbrochhaus.com/pelican.html"&gt;older&lt;/a&gt;), but had to supplement those with various official docs along the way when I was in unfamiliar territory (which was approximately all of the time). I think I also had to add in a few tweaks for things that have changed since those posts were written. You could get most of this by just reading his posts (and I recommend clicking through), but I wanted the experience of writing it out. I've tried to include the most relevant extra links inline below where they were helpful to me - let me know if I missed something super useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Local Python setup&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's install some packages. I'm using &lt;a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/virtualenv"&gt;&lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to choose a specific Python interpreter and maintain an isolated set of packages relevant to this project. I'm also using &lt;a href="http://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.org/en/latest/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is a wrapper for &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt; that simplifies the API and makes it a little more friendly to use. Source &lt;code&gt;virtualenvwrapper.sh&lt;/code&gt; and let it set things up with defaults (if you want to override the defaults, open the script and see what environment variables to set before you source the file). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo pip install virtualenv
sudo pip install virtualenvwrapper
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# optionally export the correct environment vars used in the shell script &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;#   (if you want to override the defaults)&lt;/span&gt;
. /usr/local/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Aside: through the process of setting up this project, I'm starting to finally grok &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt;, and I suspect that &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; (via e.g. &lt;code&gt;easy_install&lt;/code&gt;), &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/code&gt; are among a small number of python packages that should ever be &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; installed, system-wide.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a new virtualenv (named 'blogging', for example) with a path to your interpreter (e.g. the result of &lt;code&gt;which python&lt;/code&gt; or whichever installation you'd like to use), and &lt;code&gt;pip install&lt;/code&gt; the relevant packages into that virtualenv (feel free to steal my &lt;a href="https://github.com/jrmontag/blog/blob/master/requirements.txt"&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/a&gt; and run &lt;code&gt;pip install -r requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt;). These packages will also install a bunch of others as dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;mkvirtualenv -p /path/to/.../python2.7 blogging     &lt;span class="c"&gt;# for example&lt;/span&gt;
pip install -r /path/to/.../requirements.txt
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# optionally check the currently-installed packages -- a handy cmd to know&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;#   (this is like &amp;#39;pip freeze&amp;#39; for the active virtualenv) &lt;/span&gt;
lssitepackages
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, I'm using Python 2.7.6 for this environment. A couple of other &lt;code&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/code&gt; commands that you'll want to know: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;workon              &lt;span class="c"&gt;# list the existing virtualenvs (also visible at ~/.virtualenv) &lt;/span&gt;
workon your_env     &lt;span class="c"&gt;# enter the your_env virtualenv (prompt will change) &lt;/span&gt;
deactivate          &lt;span class="c"&gt;# exit current virtualenv, return to system environment&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Local project setup&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part is pretty subjective. Ultimately, we're going to have a git repository involved, but I'm actually keeping it above the root of my project tree for now. I have a &lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt; directory at the bottom level and am planning to keep e.g. icon and theme directories in there, too. Soon, we'll create a git repository in the &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; directory to hold our content. First, use the handy Pelican &lt;a href="https://pelican.readthedocs.org/en/3.2/getting_started.html#kickstart-your-site"&gt;quickstart&lt;/a&gt; command to set up the rest of the project structure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;mkdir -p ~/blog/src
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/blog/src
workon blogging     &lt;span class="c"&gt;# or whatever you named your env (and if you aren&amp;#39;t already in it)&lt;/span&gt;
pelican-quickstart
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't worry too much about the questions - I just hit enter for all of them to use the default settings. While still in the &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; directory, initialize a new git repository (&lt;code&gt;git init&lt;/code&gt;) and create a &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file with the lines below. We're excluding the compiled, swap, and output (mostly html and CSS) files. The content of &lt;code&gt;output/&lt;/code&gt; will end up in our &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch (more on this shortly). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;# add these to your .gitignore&lt;/span&gt;
*.pyc
*.swp
*.pid       &lt;span class="c"&gt;# this gets created by the develop_server.sh script&lt;/span&gt;
output/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's sync the repo before we move on. Create a new project repository on GitHub, and skip the "Initialize this repository with a README" part. Grab the ssh address and bring it over to your new local repo. Set the upstream remote / master and add all your new content: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;# assuming you&amp;#39;ve created the new-repo repository on github&lt;/span&gt;
git add -A
git commit -m&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;initial commit&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; 
git remote add origin new-repo_ssh-address
git push -u origin master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If that went well, you can cruise over the repo on GitHub and make sure all your files are there (and hopefully no &lt;code&gt;output/&lt;/code&gt; directory because we included it in the &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to write your first post. Our articles are going in the &lt;code&gt;src/content/&lt;/code&gt; directory. Pelican supports both &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.3.0/getting_started.html#file-metadata"&gt;reStructuredText and Markdown&lt;/a&gt;. The article syntax is different for the two filetypes, so when you pick one, check that link for the proper headings. If you want to just get started using Markdown, then create a simple new file like the one below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;# create a file called hello-world.md in src/content/ &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;#   with something like the text below... &lt;/span&gt;
Tite: Hello World!
Date: 2014-01-01
Tags: pelican
Slug: hello-world
Author: Clark Kent
Summary: In which the author writes their first blog post.

We&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;re blogging with Pelican!
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now that you have some content, time to let Pelican do it's thing. The &lt;code&gt;pelican-quickstart&lt;/code&gt; process should have created a Makefile in your &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; directory with some helpful commands for blog development. One of those is labeled &lt;code&gt;devserver&lt;/code&gt; and it lets you view the current state of your &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory, locally at port 8000. You can look through what &lt;code&gt;make devserver&lt;/code&gt; does (it calls the &lt;code&gt;develop_server.sh&lt;/code&gt; shell script, which in turn calls on Pelican...) or just use it for now and understand it later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all went as planned, you should be able to point a browser to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:8000/&lt;/code&gt; and see your new blog, live and kicking. Well, live in the only-exists-on-your-machine-while-devserver-is-running kind of way. But it's a start. For now, kill the local devserver process (cntl-C, followed by &lt;code&gt;./develop_server.sh stop&lt;/code&gt; because cntl-C seemingly doesn't fully kill the process), and let's put this content somewhere where others can see it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;GitHub Pages setup&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub is amazingly powerful for a host of reasons. One of those is the ability to set up a low-... actually a basically zero-overhead website to display your projects via &lt;a href="http://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. A couple of stellar examples are the docs for &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; - a static website generator similar to Pelican but in Ruby - and Cam Davidson-Pilon's &lt;a href="http://camdavidsonpilon.github.io/Probabilistic-Programming-and-Bayesian-Methods-for-Hackers/"&gt;Probabilistic Programming book&lt;/a&gt;. These are also great examples of having your content served through a custom domain (Jekyll) or from the default GitHub address of your project (Probabilistic...). [Tangent: I'm working through Davidson-Pilon's book right now and I highly recommend it if you're into that sort of thing.] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, we'll use the latter and return to talk about custom domain names another time. To serve static content from a GitHub repo, you need a &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch as part of your project repo. If you're a git wizard and are already adept at managing branches, this may seem anticlimactic but we can use a &lt;a href="https://github.com/davisp/ghp-import"&gt;really handy script&lt;/a&gt; that manages the &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch for us. To quote the docs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This saves me from even having to think about the branch and everything becomes magical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what &lt;code&gt;ghp-import&lt;/code&gt; was written for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you used the &lt;code&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt; file from my project when setting up your virtualenv, you should already have &lt;code&gt;ghp-import&lt;/code&gt; installed (but recall that you can also check with &lt;code&gt;lssitepackages&lt;/code&gt;). The &lt;code&gt;pelican-quickstart&lt;/code&gt; command should have also added a &lt;code&gt;make github&lt;/code&gt; portion to the Makefile. The pieces are falling into place like magic. The final step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;make github
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's it. That make command actually does quite a lot, so definitely dig through the sequence of events there, but not right now. Right now, you should do two things: first, check that your repo has a new branch called &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; and then check that you can go to &lt;code&gt;https://your-user-name.github.io/new-repo-name&lt;/code&gt;. (I'll totally understand if you do the second part first.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With luck (and minimal misleading mistakes on my part), you are well on your way. I've got a few other helpful upgrades to the base setup and will try to share any other future upgrades that might be helpful, too. Until then, happy blogging with your new GitHub Pages-hosted Pelican site. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="python"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="git"></category><category term="weekend"></category></entry><entry><title>hello world</title><link href="http://joshmontague.com/posts/2014/hello-world/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Josh Montague</name></author><id>tag:joshmontague.com,2014-01-01:posts/2014/hello-world/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My 2014 resolutions are completely and shamelessly copied from slash inspired by my friend &lt;a href="http://semi-rad.com/2013/12/do-things-and-make-things-next-year"&gt;Brendan Leonard&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is step 1 of Make Things. More to come. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pelican"></category></entry></feed>